I think the [music] best fiction is the fiction that has this blurry line between what's personal and what's universal. What's detailed and what's [music] abstract?
あたしが思うに、最高のフィクションって、個人的なものと普遍的なものの間に、このぼやけた線があるフィクションなんだ。細かいものと、抽象的なものって、何？
There has to be some sort of truth for me in it. But at the same time, I think it's much more about the other. If you are [music] writing from this place, then you can sing from this place.
その中には、あたしにとってなんらかの真実がないとダメなんだ。でも同時に、ずっと他者のことだと思う。この場所から書いてるなら、この場所から歌えるんだよ。
I promised [music] myself I was going to make an album where I was going to finish the thought, finish the song, go all the way until the end.
自分に約束したんだ、思考を最後まで終わらせて、曲を終わらせて、最後まで行き切るアルバムを作るって。
Motoami was minimalist. This is maximalism. So much to talk to you about about this album. Thank you for making this. I don't even know if it's an album.
MOTOMAMIはミニマリストだった。これはマキシマリズムだ。このアルバムについて君に話したいことがすごくたくさんある。これを作ってくれてありがとう。これ、アルバムなのかすらわからない。
That's the best in the sense that that's the best compliment that somebody can say. I think it's almost like of a framework for this this music that you've made.
それは最高、って意味で、誰かが言える最高の褒め言葉なんだ。君が作ったこの音楽の、なんか枠組みみたいなものだと思う。
It's so much you could but we're in Madrid and um you're causing chaos and you've launched your album here [snorts] and you're running around getting fine sitting [laughter] up politicians and doing what you should be doing.
できることはすごく多いけど、ぼくたちはマドリードにいて、うん、君はカオスを起こしてて、ここでアルバムを出して、走り回って罰金食らって、政治家を座らせて、やるべきことをやってる。
Oh my goodness. But it looked like you had a lot of fun. I just I just wanted to go um see the cartel, go see the lights, you can go outside and yeah, but it's a fun moment.
ああ、とんでもない。でも君、すごく楽しそうだった。あたしはただ、ただポスターを見に行きたかったんだ、ライトを見に。外に出られるし、うん、でも楽しい瞬間だよ。
It's a it's a beautiful moment, you know, when Okay, now the the album is finished finally. And now it's about sharing it.
きれいな瞬間なんだよね、わかる？ よし、やっとアルバムが終わった。で、今はそれをシェアすることなんだ。
It can be discouraging sometimes how long it takes, but I think it's teaching me patience. Each project is teaching me more patience.
どれだけ時間がかかるか、落ち込むこともある。でも忍耐を教えてくれてると思う。プロジェクトごとに、もっと忍耐を教えてくれる。
Well, you must have had so much patience to just get through this process of making this album because there's so much in it.
まあ、このアルバムを作る過程をただ乗り越えるのに、君、ものすごい忍耐がいったよね。だって中身がすごく多いから。
Yes. I I loved what you said about Leonard Cohen and the idea of finishing a record in the three stages.
うん。レナード・コーエンについて君が言ってたこと、レコードを三つの段階で仕上げるってアイデア、すごく好きだった。
That area where it can just you can just feel very lost in it. It's no longer yours. It takes on a life of its own. That must have been many moments during the making of this.
あの領域、ただその中でとても迷子になれるところ。もう君のものじゃなくなる。勝手に命を持ち始める。これを作ってる間、そういう瞬間がたくさんあったよね。
It felt that way. Yes. Because it's been 3 years. So all the things that can happen in three years. So many.
そう感じた。うん。だって三年あったから。三年で起こりうること、全部。すごくたくさん。
But also I love that Leona is a big inspiration and I love that he used to say which I would repeat a lot while I was making the album.
でもレナードが大きなインスピレーションなのも好きで、彼がよく言ってたこと、アルバム作ってる間あたしが何度も繰り返してたのが好きなんだ。
He used to say uh forget your perfect offering. There is a crack in everything. That's how the light gets in. Mhm.
彼はよく言ってた、完璧な捧げものは忘れな、って。すべてにひびがある。そこから光が入るんだ。うん。
And I think that I I wanted the light to get in and I wanted it to be called looks. How to make more space for the light to get in.
光に入ってほしいと思ったし、LUXって呼びたかった。光が入るスペースをもっとどう作るか。
I love that you refer to light as seen through the cracks and not necessarily the light that's all around us at all times. Sometimes we shield ourselves from the light or the light can be too bright.
君が光を、ひびを通して見えるものとして言ってるのが好きなんだ。必ずしも、いつでも周りにある光じゃなくて。ときどき人は光から自分を守るし、光は明るすぎることもある。
But you're right that the light that cracks in is a is is different, isn't it? It's um there's a glimmer of what of what's available to you there hasn't yet revealed itself.
でも君の言う通り、ひび割れて入ってくる光は違うんだよね？ なんか、まだ自分を現してない、君に使えるもののきらめきがある。
Yes. Yes. The possibility the outside. Yeah. And beyond.
うん。うん。可能性、外側。うん。そしてその向こう。
But when you're working on music, can you exist in a functional societal social way or do you need to sort of consciously remove yourself from the normal side of being a human and
でも音楽をやってるとき、機能する社会的な、ソーシャルなやり方で存在できるの？ それとも人間でいる普通の側から、意識的に自分を外す必要があるの、そして
a friend? Yeah, I kind of I think I kind of isolate, but at the same time, I listen myself and if I'm like, okay, it's been maybe a week that I don't see nobody except
友達でいることから？ うん、なんか、孤立すると思う。でも同時に自分を聴いてて、もし、オッケー、誰にも会ってないのがたぶん一週間、除いて
these uh friends that I'm working with in the studio, which I consider friends. Dan, uh David, which I've been working with for like six years at this point.
スタジオで一緒に働いてるこの友達たち、友達だと思ってる。ダン、それとデイヴィッド、この時点で六年くらい一緒に働いてる。
He's an amazing engineer. I became an a friend here through this project. So yeah, I feel like I hang a lot in the studio. It's a lot of hanging in the studio.
彼はすごいエンジニアなんだ。このプロジェクトを通して、ここで友達になった。だからうん、スタジオに長く居る感じ。スタジオでだらだらするのが多いんだ。
But at the same time, there's a lot of being alone at home, writing, reading, writing, reading. Just one year of that. Yeah.
でも同時に、家で一人でいるのも多い、書いて、読んで、書いて、読んで。それをまる一年。うん。
It was an entire year. I remember guys were like, "We need you. You need to come back to the studio." And I was like, "I can't. No, I won't.
まる一年だった。覚えてる、みんなが「君が必要なんだ。スタジオに戻ってこないと」みたいで。あたしは「できない。いや、やらない。
I have to make lyrics. And these lyrics are not good enough. I'm going to keep working on lyrics. I'm going to stay here working on lyrics until this is great."
歌詞を作らないと。この歌詞はまだ良くない。歌詞を作り続ける。ここにとどまって、これが最高になるまで歌詞をやる」って。
And then more music. When you were touring Motoami, you had been in this brilliant modern loop that we're all in, which is like album, tour, Lucy, like a song, maybe collaboration.
それからもっと音楽。君がMOTOMAMIをツアーしてたとき、みんながいるこの見事な現代のループの中にいた、アルバム、ツアー、ルーシー、みたいな曲、たぶんコラボ。
This doesn't feel like that. It's like you stopped that hard. And yes, this is what I needed.
これはそういう感じじゃない。君がそれを強く止めたみたい。そしてうん、これがあたしに必要だったんだ。
I feel like I always do projects, find the excuse to study what I want to study and go through what I want to go through and feel like my my heart is is
いつもプロジェクトをやって、勉強したいことを勉強する言い訳を見つけて、通りたいことを通って、心が
needing and it's craving and in this case it was reading more and it was studying more.
求めてて、渇望してて、今回はもっと読むこと、もっと勉強することだった、って感じがする。
If I was not uh having a a musical career, I would probably just be listening in the in college the I just wanted to like be studying the that's what I kind of
もし音楽のキャリアがなかったら、たぶん大学で聴いてるだけだった、ただ勉強してたかった、それがなんか
tried to like just study learn more about spirituality in a in a make ores of what spirituality is understanding how saintthood it's understood and and and conce ceive differently depending on the the
ただ勉強して、スピリチュアリティについてもっと学ぼうとした、スピリチュアリティとは何かのメイク・オーレスの中で、聖人であることがどう理解されて、どう違うふうに捉えられるか、その
cultures and and religions different religions and how interesting is that for example in Christianismo there's a very specific way of understanding saint saintthood but then there's equivalence in other religions so in Hinduism
文化と、宗教、違う宗教、それがどれだけ面白いか、たとえばクリスティアニスモでは聖人であることを理解するすごく特定のやり方があって、でも他の宗教に等価なものがある、だからヒンドゥー教では
there's the rishes which are these mstros savio there's I don't know the shan they are immortals in the tow in Judaism amigos God's friends they call it in Islam like they there all
リシェがいて、このムストロス・サヴィオで、知らない、シャン、彼らはタオの中の不死者、ユダヤ教ではアミーゴス、神の友達って呼ぶ、イスラムでは、みたいに、彼ら全部
around the world you can find different ways of understanding saintthood and that was so interesting to me I was like okay wait there's all these stories about saints I was trying to pull
世界中にいて、聖人であることの違う理解の仕方が見つかる、それがすごく面白くて、オッケー待って、聖人についての物語が全部ある、引っ張ろうとしてた
from like all these crazy amazing stories from all around the world I put uh mapundi in the room and I started uh reading halographas just reading reading reading reading and I just tried
世界中のこのクレイジーで、すごい物語から、部屋にマプンディを置いて、ハログラファスを読み始めて、ただ読んで読んで読んで読んで、ただ
to like understand where did they come from which was the language that would be um spoken there um what was the story behind so there was a lot of women like that were
彼らがどこから来たか理解しようとした、そこで話される言語はどれか、背景の物語は何か、だからそういう女性がたくさんいて
extremely interesting to me that they were nuns they were poets and I was like okay I'm going to read uh about them I'm going to read what they actually wrote.
すごく面白くて、修道女で、詩人で、オッケー、彼女たちについて読む、実際に書いたものを読む、って。
I'm going to uh try to explain these stories. I think it's important to while collecting stories about the other.
これらの物語を説明しようとした。他者についての物語を集めながら、それが大事だと思う。
I feel like then making songs inspired in that like I'm celebrating and giving love to the other to the otherness trying to understand the otherness better.
それから、それにインスパイアされて曲を作るのは、他者を、他者性を祝って、愛を与えて、他者性をもっと理解しようとしてる感じなんだ。
It feels like nowadays is like everything is so divided and and and no I want the opposite. I I need the opposite. At least that's how I feel.
今は全部がすごく分断されてる感じで、いや、逆が欲しい。逆が必要なんだ。少なくともそう感じてる。
This deep curiosity that informs this music, it is a huge part of what is is so um immersive for us about it.
この音楽を形作ってるこの深い好奇心、それが、ぼくたちにとってこれがすごく没入的な、すごく大きな部分なんだ。
I'm always interested in how artists can move so deeply into quote unquote conceptual environments, but it has to be about you.
アーティストが、いわゆるコンセプチュアルな環境に、こんなに深く動いていけるのがいつも気になる。でもそれは君のことじゃないと。
It can't just be an essay about me.
あたしについてのエッセイだけじゃダメなんだ。
These songs you don't feel are about you. I think though that it's an album that fortunately or unfortunately it will have pieces of me, little pieces of me.
この曲たちは君のことには感じない、って君は感じる。でも幸いにも、不幸にも、あたしの断片、小さなかけらが入るアルバムだと思う。
But I think the best fiction is the the fiction that has this blurry line. There's a blurry line like the sweet spot between what's personal and what's universal.
でも最高のフィクションは、このぼやけた線があるフィクションだと思う。ぼやけた線がある、個人的なものと普遍的なものの間のスイートスポットみたいな。
What's detailed and what's abstract? maybe what's uh implicit and what it's explicit. It's both.
何が細かくて、何が抽象的？ たぶん何が暗示的で、何が明示的か。両方なんだ。
And so I think that yeah, obviously because I wrote it, there has to be some sort of like truth for me in it. But at the same time, I think it's much more about the other than about myself.
だからうん、明らかに書いたから、その中にあたしにとってのなんらかの真実がないと。でも同時に、自分自身より他者についての方がずっと多いと思う。
Although there was going to be moments and and specific things, journey, for example, Reikia.
とはいえ瞬間や、具体的なものがあることになる、ジャーニー、たとえばReliquia。
Yeah. That has journey that has about I've been here and I've been there. but it's inspired in Santa Rosa de Lima and and how her selikas are spread around the world.
うん。それにはジャーニーがある、ここにいた、あそこにいた、っていう。でもSanta Rosa de Limaにインスパイアされてて、彼女のセリカスが世界中に広がってる。
So there's there was so many like crazy coincidences while I was studying and learning about these stories.
だから、これらの物語を勉強して学んでる間、クレイジーな偶然がすごくたくさんあった。
Santa Rosalia um Hilaring Bimala there was crazy stories Santa so many women that yeah that were amazing and that I wanted to kind of in a way channel their stories.
サンタ・ロサリア、うーんヒラリング・ビマラ、クレイジーな物語があった、サンタ、すごくたくさんの女性、うん、素晴らしくて、ある意味彼女たちの物語をチャネルしたかった。
But I love the character studies that that that you created on this record and but at the same time the way that you perform these songs the emotion that you instill in in
でもこのレコードで君が作ったキャラクター・スタディが好きで、でも同時に、これらの曲をパフォーマンスするやり方、注ぎ込む感情
these songs when you sing them. Yes. It's hard for me as a listener and a fan to not feel that you are feeling something deep within yourself.
歌うときのこれらの曲に。うん。聞き手として、ファンとして、君が自分の奥深くで何かを感じてる、って感じないのは難しい。
Personal growth. I agree though. I agree.
個人的な成長。でも同意する。同意するよ。
I think it's more internal like when you get to Magnolia's I can't believe at the end that you're not projecting forward into the end of what has been a wonderful adventure true to
もっと内面的だと思う、マグノリアに着くと、最後に、素晴らしい冒険だったものの終わりに向かって君が前に投影してないなんて信じられない、忠実に
to put the perfect ribbon on it right kind of yes but it's inspired in an Mima she had an amazing burial there was so many flowers like it crazy and apparently everybody felt
それに完璧なリボンを結ぶ、だよね、みたいな、うん、でもミマにインスパイアされてて、彼女はすごい埋葬があった、花がすごくたくさん、クレイジーで、どうやらみんな感じた
so in peace apparently everybody was outside everybody felt so much peace and like joy and so for me I was like wait This is amazing to know that that happened and I'm like
すごく平和に、どうやらみんな外にいて、みんなすごく平和と、喜びみたいなものを感じて、だからあたしは、待って、これが起きたって知るのはすごい、って
how how would my me and the how would my burial be? Maybe it's just about please don't be sad when I die. Just please have a party.
どう、あたしの、あたしの埋葬はどうなる？ たぶんただ、死んでも悲しまないで、ってこと。ただパーティーをして。
Yeah, that was what uh for me what was I was asking.
うん、それが、あたしにとって、問うてたことだった。
And in the back of my um in my back I have a tattoo that it's um something that Manuel Molina wrote which is my favorite writer in Spain.
そして背中に、背中にタトゥーがあって、それはマヌエル・モリーナが書いたもの、スペインで一番好きな作家なんだ。
My favorite writer in Spain. He said He's saying nobody better nobody cry the day that I die.
スペインで一番好きな作家。彼は言った、彼は言ってる、誰も、誰も泣かない方がいい、あたしが死ぬ日は。
It's more beautiful to cry even if you cry with sadness.
悲しみで泣いても、泣く方が美しい。
So even if okay you're going to have maybe some sadness but still like just just have fun just enjoy.
だから、オッケー、いくらか悲しみがあるかもしれないとしても、それでもただ楽しんで、ただ味わって。
There must have been a lot of times during the making of this record though when you felt a very powerful emotion. And I can't imagine working with the London Symphony Orchestra.
でもこのレコードを作ってる間、すごく強い感情を感じたときがたくさんあったよね。それにLondon Symphony Orchestraと働くなんて想像できない。
Yeah. I mean, that's out of control. Crazy. That was crazy. I definitely had chills so many times while making Definitely making uh vocals, recording vocals. I don't think I ever cried so much making an album.
うん。つまり、制御不能。クレイジー。クレイジーだった。間違いなく、作ってる間何度も鳥肌が立った。間違いなくボーカルを作って、ボーカルを録って。アルバム作りでこんなに泣いたことはないと思う。
I don't think I've ever ever ever cried so much recording vocals. And I think that I didn't I didn't maybe want to go through this before. I was like, I'm not ready.
ボーカルを録って、こんなに、こんなに、こんなに泣いたことはないと思う。そして、たぶん以前はこれを通りたくなかった。まだ準備できてない、って。
I know I had to do an album like this, but I wasn't ready yet.
こういうアルバムをやらなきゃいけないのはわかってた。でもまだ準備できてなかった。
How did you know? How did you know that after Motoami, which was a resounding success, one of the most amazing tours, beautiful high concept art, dynamics, just lot of movement, everything.
どうやってわかったの？ どうやってわかったの、MOTOMAMIのあと、大成功で、いちばんすごいツアーのひとつ、美しいハイコンセプトのアート、ダイナミクス、ただ動きがたくさん、全部。
I mean, you got to be happy at the end of that. Then how did you know that I have not gone deep enough?
つまり、あれの終わりには幸せなはずだよね。じゃあどうやって、まだ十分深く行ってない、ってわかったの？
I need to like not even close. It's so different. Ah, there was something that my sister said that stuck with me when I played Moto Mommy for her.
まだ近くにもない、みたいに必要。すごく違う。ああ、姉が言ったことで残ったものがあった、MOTOMAMIを彼女に聴かせたとき。
What' she say? Okay, so we were in the car. I played for her. She pointed out this kind of like musical Tourett or something.
彼女、何て言ったの？ オッケー、車の中にいた。彼女に聴かせた。彼女がこの、なんか音楽のトゥレットみたいなものを指摘した。
This this sort of like kind of like why do you have to destroy the song always?
この、なんか、なんでいつも曲を壊さないといけないの、みたいな。
Yeah, that's Billy, right? That's my nonchalan. You love [laughter] the ones that love you back, right? The only ones who get away with that.
うん、それはビリーだよね？ ぼくのノンシャランだ。愛を返してくれる人を愛するよね。それで許されるのはその人たちだけ。
Yes. That's my nonchalan sister [laughter] and my best friend, which I love so much. And and she said that and when she said that, it hurt so bad cuz I was like, what are you talking about?
うん。あれはあたしのノンシャランな姉で、一番の友達、すごく愛してる。そして彼女がそう言って、言われたときすごく痛かった、何言ってるの、って。
I started fighting her and I started being like, what are you talking about? No, no, no, because you don't get it. I'm trying to like, yes, this this makes sense.
彼女と戦い始めて、何言ってるの？ いや、いや、いや、だってわかってない。うん、これは筋が通る、ってしようとしてる。
This disruption here, da da da. But at the end of the day, it stuck with me because I'm like, "Wait, why do I make music?
ここのこの破壊、ダダダ。でも結局残った、だって「待って、なんで音楽を作るの？
I make music for people to feel, right? And maybe they're going to feel the most if I really go all the way.
人が感じるために音楽を作るんだよね？ そして本当に最後まで行ったら、いちばん感じるかもしれない。
How can I?" Cuz maybe I'm not allowing myself to go all the way. Maybe I'm writing songs, but I'm not finishing the thought. So, I was like, I'm going to make the next album.
どうやったら？」 だって、最後まで行くことを自分に許してないかもしれない。曲は書いてるけど、思考を終わらせてない。だから、次のアルバムを作る、って。
I promised myself I was going to make an album where I was going to at least try at least try to finish the thought, finish the song
自分に約束した、少なくとも試す、少なくとも思考を終わらせることを試す、曲を終わらせるアルバムを作るって。
go all the way until the end. And I think that in this album, it allowed me to grow as a as a writer and as an arranger and as a producer because of that, because
最後まで行き切る。そしてこのアルバムでは、それで、書き手として、アレンジャーとして、プロデューサーとして成長させてくれたと思う、なぜなら
of going all the way and not trying to just, you know, break the song here and there. No, like this is the thought how far I can go with this thought.
最後まで行くこと、そしてただ、ほら、あちこちで曲を壊すだけ、じゃない。いや、これが思考で、この思考でどこまで行けるか。
In a way, you still retain some loyalty to that idea of being um free with arrangements and break things and there are movements in each song, but
ある意味、アレンジで自由でいること、壊すことへの忠誠はまだ残してる、各曲に動きはある、でも
because you're moving in a space that has long been considered archaic or ancient or old-fashioned, Mhm.
君が動いてる空間は、長いこと古風とか、古代とか、時代遅れと考えられてきたから。うん。
You know, this idea of working in symphony, Baroque art and inspiration, things that you study, y like remember how it used to be hundreds of years ago.
わかる、シンフォニーで働くってアイデア、バロックのアートとインスピレーション、勉強する物事、何百年も前はどうだったか思い出すみたいな。
Yes. But why can't it be as powerful today as it was back then? And it definitely can. And I think that at least I'm always my feeling is always I'm in service of the emotion.
うん。でもなんで今日、当時と同じくらいパワフルじゃいけないの？ そして絶対できる。そして少なくとも、感覚はいつも、感情に仕えてる。
So yes, this album don't have loops and it's very intentional that it doesn't have loops. That was kind of a rule. We were like, we were not going to do no loops.
だからうん、このアルバムはループを持ってない、ループがないのはすごく意図的なんだ。なんかルールだった。あたしたち、ループはやらない、ノー・ループはやらない、って。
We have this in the back of our heads.
これは頭の後ろにある。
Even at the end of divin when it gets super frantic and anxious.
ディヴィンの終わりでも、すごく取り乱して、不安になるとき。
Yeah. Yes. Yes. Yes. Yes. There's no loop in it. It's play played or the vocals. Even if there's like a repetition in a melody, still it's sung.
うん。うん。うん。うん。うん。その中にループはない。演奏されてる、あるいはボーカル。メロディに繰り返しがあっても、それでも歌われてる。
There's there's like the conscious decision of not using loops humans.
ループを使わない、人間たち、って意識的な決断がある。
Yeah. So it's like how do I go from point A to point B? How do I how do I instead of from A to B?
うん。だからポイントAからポイントBにどう行く？ AからBの代わりに、どう、どう？
Boom. Next. Yes. No. No. No. No. No. No. No. go through the experience as if the experience is the the the most important is the journey. It's not about getting to from point A to B.
ドーン。次。うん。いや。いや。いや。いや。いや。いや。いや。体験を通り抜ける、体験がいちばん大事みたいに。旅なんだ。ポイントAからBに着くことじゃない。
It's go through it. Let yourself go through it. And I I wanted that it was acoustic instruments. I everything it feels I think it feels like that human wood.
通り抜けるんだ。自分に通り抜けさせて。そしてアコースティックの楽器であってほしかった。全部、そう感じると思う、人間の木って感じ。
Um it feels like the space feels entirely immersive like the space.
うーん、空間が完全に没入的に感じる、空間みたいに。
Yeah. materialist physicality. Um, so at the end of the day, you have the sense, the feeling that there's a human in there. There's humans in there. It's made by a human.
うん。マテリアリストな物理性。うーん、結局、感覚がある、中に人間がいるって感覚。中に人間たちがいる。人間が作ったんだ。
It's about love and from love hopefully. Well, love is in every single iteration. I mean adoration, uninterrupted, unfettered pure obsession, then judgment, conditional forgiveness, um, hate, anger, violence, a lot of violence on this room.
愛についてで、願わくば愛から。まあ、愛はあらゆる反復にある。つまり崇拝、途切れない、縛られない純粋な執着、それから判断、条件付きの許し、うーん、憎しみ、怒り、暴力、この部屋には暴力がたくさん。
Also, also enough of what I needed. I felt like I needed to be in it. I think beyond, but it's not a glorifying evil.
それに、それに、必要だったものは足りてた。その中にいる必要を感じた。向こうだと思う、でも悪を賛美してるわけじゃない。
As a protagonist, it feels like to me as a as a as a writer of this experience, either others experience brought to life through your filter or your own experience
主人公として、この体験の書き手としてのぼくには感じる、他者の体験が君のフィルターを通して生かされるか、君自身の体験か
the mixture of the abstract and the literal. Yes.
抽象的なものと文字通りのものの混ぜ合わせ。うん。
That in the middle of all of that, there is confusion about what it all means. You're asking if there is some I'm asking you if it was written out of pure instinct.
その全部の真ん中で、それが全部何を意味するかの混乱がある。何かがあるか君が聞いてる、ぼくは純粋な本能から書かれたのか君に聞いてる。
Uhhuh. Or experience. Oo, that's a tough one.
うんうん。それとも経験から。おお、それは難しい。
Um I think it starts with instinct and I think that later there's a there's this moment where you just analyze with cold head you are curic about it but it's pretty much I
うーん、本能から始まると思う、そしてあとで、冷たい頭で分析する瞬間がある、それについて気になってる、でもほとんど、あたしは
think everything usually for me it's pretty much intuitive I don't rationalize it too much I try to nurture myself with um whatever I feel like I need to explain and later so I
思う、全部はふつう、あたしにとってはだいたい直感的、あんまり理性にしすぎない、説明する必要があると感じるもので自分を養おうとする、そしてあとで、だから
let it happen in if you nurture yourself the right way you're going to be able to explain it be the vessel and explain it and so later I think that uh I start
それが起こるに任せる、正しいやり方で自分を養えば、説明できるようになる、器になって、それを説明できる、だからあとであたしは
rationalizing it when I see what's what I'm doing I don't think I'm thinking what I'm doing when I'm doing it okay let me be specific about like me and Christie yeah yeah okay
やってるのが何なのかが見えたときに理性的にし始める、やってるときに何をやってるか考えてるとは思わない、オッケー、ぼくとクリスティみたいに具体的にしよう、うんうんオッケー
that one it took me a whole year I'm not surprised a whole year to do yeah and thank you for seeing it through that [snorts] remarkable piece of music, but
あれはまる一年かかった、驚かない、やるのにまる一年、うん、そしてそれを最後まで見てくれてありがとう、驚くべき音楽のピース、でも
as as a a sentiment, a story, is it a generalized um appreciation or is it a specific appreciation about one person or something specific because it's so delicately written?
感情として、物語として、一般的な鑑賞なの？ それとも一人についての具体的な鑑賞、それとも何か具体的なもの？ だってすごく繊細に書かれてるから。
Um I think that uh the whole project has that balance and definitely I found very very beautiful very very inspiring when I found out about Santa Clara de San Francisco apparently they had
うーん、プロジェクト全体にそのバランスがあると思う、そして間違いなく、すごくすごく美しくてすごくすごくインスパイアされた、サンタ・クララ・デ・サンフランシスコについて知ったとき、どうやら彼らには
this really really really strong friendship and this very strong bond and that was beautiful and I was like okay let me let me experience uh how to write about is about this friendship.
このすごくすごくすごく強い友情と、このすごく強い絆があって、それが美しくて、オッケー、この友情について、これについて書くのを体験させて、って。
How how would that be? And you have friendship that is similar. You could create you could refer back to your own experience in that way.
それはどうなる？ そして似てる友情がある。そのやり方で、自分の経験に戻って参照して作れただろう。
I mean the whole album has has that has a truth on on what I've experienced for sure cuz otherwise I couldn't write it and especially it's also in Italian.
つまりアルバム全体にそれがある、経験したことに真実がある、確実に、そうじゃなきゃ書けなかった、そして特にイタリア語でもある。
I try to write first in Spanish h a lot a lot a lot of it and then I would send it to a translator and also would use Google translate.
最初はスペイン語で書こうとした、すごく、すごく、すごくたくさん、それから翻訳者に送って、グーグル翻訳も使った。
So I would like kind of like uh go back and forth with that for an entire year of writing.
だから書くまる一年、それと行ったり来たりしてた。
Uh it took me a lot of attempts in front of in front of the piano of trying to make the area and I would remember like I would talk with Noah and I
うーん、ピアノの前で、前で、ariaを作ろうとしてたくさんの試みがかかった、そしてノアと話して、覚えてる
would say I want I really want to make an area. I want to write an area but I need time to study.
言ってた、ariaを作りたい、本当にariaを書きたい、でも勉強する時間が必要、って。
I need time to understand how an area is, how an area is written, how usually the structures are or and let's see. And so it took me a year in Miami, writing in Miami in this house in Miami.
ariaがどういうものか理解する時間が必要、ariaがどう書かれるか、ふつう構造がどうか、そして見てみよう。だからマイアミで一年かかった、マイアミのこの家で書いて。
I finally found it. I found the just improvising. I found the the hook in the piano, very very little uh notes with the left hand just to understand a little bit how the chords could be.
やっと見つけた。即興するだけで見つけた。ピアノのフックを見つけた、左手のすごくすごく少ない音で、コードがどうなりうるか少し理解するために。
And then I brought it to LA. I kept working on it. And then one day finally I got to the studio and I was like finally I have the area.
それからLAに持っていった。作業を続けた。そしてある日やっとスタジオに着いて、やっとariaがある、って。
What an ara what I say what I call an area. I don't even know if it's an ara okay but but it's inspired.
なんてaria、あたしが言うもの、あたしがariaと呼ぶもの。ariaなのかすらわからない、オッケー、でもインスパイアされてる。
Yes. Yes it's it honors that the communication that comes through the record in multiple languages 14 I think languages.
うん。うん、それはレコードを通ってくるコミュニケーションを称えてる、複数の言語で、十四だと思う、言語。
But anytime that it switches from Catalan or Spanish into Japanese it's very natural to the point where I had to look at the lyrics and be reminded that you was even singing in
でもカタルーニャ語やスペイン語から日本語に切り替わるときはいつでも、すごく自然で、歌詞を見ないと、君が日本語で歌ってたことさえ思い出せないところまで。
Japanese. That makes me happy man. That makes me so happy because because you made them your own. So why did you choose to have that moment of self-reflection?
それが嬉しい。それがすごく嬉しい、だって君がそれらを自分のものにしたから。だからなんで、その自己反省の瞬間を選んだの？
The queen of chaos. Why did you choose to to express that in Japanese?
カオスの女王。なんでそれを日本語で表現することを選んだの？
Because there's this um saint. She was called Roneno. She was a Japanese saint. And it was very interesting the story. Apparently she she destroyed her face in order to be accepted and to be accepted to be so monaster.
だってこの、うーん、聖人がいるから。了然って呼ばれてた。日本の聖人だった。そして物語がすごく面白かった。どうやら彼女は顔を壊した、受け入れられるために、そして受け入れられるために、そう、修道院に。
She wanted to get in that monastery and be accepted in it. And she destroyed her face in order to be admitted in it. And that woman I felt like the story was insane.
その修道院に入りたかった、その中で受け入れられたかった。そして入るために顔を壊した。そしてその女性、物語が狂ってる感じがした。
That was incredible. like the the the the level of sacrifice in order for her to to achieve what she wanted and then also maybe how how a lot of times is considered craziness you know what's
それはすごかった。彼女が望むものを達成するための犠牲のレベル、そしてまた、どれだけ多くのとき狂ってると見なされるか、わかる、極端なものは
an extreme can be considered craziness or can be like catalog in that way do you think that that was extreme to do that who am I to judge what it's extreme or not
狂ってると見なされうる、あるいはそのやり方でカタログされうる。それをやるのは極端だと思う？ 何が極端か判断するあたしは誰なの
I think that each person as a different path and I'm nobody to to judge if there's extreme or not. But maybe for me as a Rosalia, it would be very hard to do something like that.
一人ひとり違う道だと思う、極端かどうか判断する立場の人間じゃない。でもロサリアとしてのあたしには、ああいうことをするのはすごく難しいだろう。
I consider it maybe extreme for who I am, but I don't consider it extreme that for her she did that.
あたしという人間には極端かもしれないと考える。でも彼女がそれをしたこと自体は極端だと考えない。
But in a way, the fact that you've gone ahead and made something so different to what you did before, you've done so much studying and learning in order to get there.
でもある意味、前にやったこととこんなに違うものを作って進んだ、そこに着くためにこんなに勉強して学んだ。
In a way, that is that is, isn't it? Continued mutilation every time you reject something you've created before in order to grow and potentially lose people in the process and leave the things that could give you comfort behind.
ある意味、それはそうなんだよね？ 成長するために、前に作った何かを拒むたびに続く切断、そして過程で人を失うかもしれなくて、安心をくれるものを後ろに残す。
Isn't that just a form of Yes, 100%. In violent change in a we in a weird way. Yes. And please, yes, every day. I hope that happens every day.
それはただの一つの形、だよね。うん、百パーセント。変な意味で、暴力的な変化の中の。うん。そしてお願い、うん、毎日。毎日そうなるといい。
I hope that every day um identity I hope that identity can always be something that it's um that it dies and borns every day and that every day you can choose who you
毎日、うーんアイデンティティが、アイデンティティがいつも、毎日死んで生まれるものでありえて、毎日誰を
are and every day you can understand who you are and you can change every day.
あるか選べて、毎日自分が誰なのか理解できて、毎日変われることを願ってる。
That's a discipline, isn't it? cuz again in your Substack um and you in your birthday post you talked about the idea of wanting to stay in all the time but then wish but then missing people's birthday parties
それは規律だよね？ だってまた君のサブスタックで、誕生日の投稿で、ずっとそこにいたいってアイデアの話をしてた、それから願う、それから人の誕生日パーティーを逃す
and events and being like man I'm just going to not get invited anymore like this you know what I mean like people just going to stop inviting me like there's FOMO here like
そしてイベント、そして、もう誘われなくなるな、みたいな、わかるよね、みたいな、人はもう誘うのをやめる、みたいな、ここにFOMOがある、みたいな
I'm missing out on so I guess I guess the question is like the idea of having the courage to move forward and leave all that behind but is there a part of you
すごく逃してる、だから質問は、前に進んで全部を後ろに残す勇気のアイデアだけど、君の一部には
that always that's that's asking are you sure you've just achieved this and people want to see you and hear you like this.
いつも、聞いてる、本当にいいの、これを達成したばかりで、人は君に会いたがって、こんな君を聴きたがってる、って。
Yeah. Yeah. But having doubt it's uh it's a proof that uh you're alive that what you're doing is it's it's truly alive. Having doubt faith they say that faith you know that it's alive because there's doubt in it.
うん。うん。でも疑いを持つことは、生きてる証明なんだ、やってることが本当に生きてるって。疑い、信仰、信仰は生きてるって言う、だってその中に疑いがあるから、わかる。
And I think here is the same.
そしてここも同じだと思う。
you you know that you are here that we're here if if but you have doubts about if you are here no probably you're feeling that doubt that doubt is reminding you that you're
ここにいるって知ってる、君はここにいる、あたしたちがここにいる、もし、もし、でもここにいるか疑いがある、いや、たぶんその疑いを感じてる、その疑いは思い出させてる、君が
alive that you're here so yeah I think that uh maybe the sacrifice sacrificing I think that um it's part of it's part of it I accept it I think I'm I'm kind of
生きてる、ここにいる、って。だからうん、たぶん犠牲、犠牲にすること、それの一部だと思う、受け入れる、なんか
in peace the more the more I grow the more I'm in peace with the fact that I'm going to miss so many things I I I would like to uh spend the whole
平和の中にいる、成長するほど、すごくたくさんのことを逃すって事実ともっと平和になる。一日中ただ
day just uh talking and vibing and being here and studying about this building and all of that. I would love to do, but I know that I won't be able that maybe we'll just have this this brief moment.
話して、ヴァイブして、ここにいて、この建物について勉強して、全部。やりたい、でもできないってわかってる、たぶんこの短い瞬間だけ。
So, I hold into it and I'm like, "Yes, okay. This is how much I'm going to see today." And and I'm okay with it. I'm not trying to too much, just a little, just enough.
だからそこにしがみつく、「うん、オッケー。今日はこれだけ見るんだ」って。そしてそれでいい。あんまりしようとしない、少しだけ、ちょうど十分。
But it it brings to light the idea of what is the present moment. Can you sit in the present moment?
でもそれは、現在の瞬間とは何か、ってアイデアを明るみに出す。現在の瞬間に座っていられる？
I'm always moving around. I I would always be like this.
いつも動き回ってる。いつもこうしてる。
So, you know, like I'm always I want to always be moving, doing things. I have to remind myself it's okay. Chill, calm down. So, yeah, I have a hard time being in the present.
だから、わかる、いつも動いてたい、物事をやってたい。自分に思い出させないといけない、いいんだ、チルして、落ち着け、って。だからうん、現在にいるのが難しい。
How do you do that? Do you do you meditate? Like what how do you find in a peace?
どうやってそれやるの？ 瞑想するの？ みたいな、平和の中にどう見つけるの？
How where do you desiring less desiring less? I'm not meditating as much these days. I'm praying more.
どう、どこで、欲を減らす、欲を減らす？ 最近はあんまり瞑想してない。もっと祈ってる。
I'd give it all away. You talk about this on the album. I'd give it all away. And you even mentioned some of the trinkets and things that we I'm learning.
全部手放す。アルバムでこれについて話してるよね。全部手放す。そして小物とか、ぼくが学んでるものにも触れてる。
I'm learning. I'm learning. I'm trying. I'm trying. It's It's a hard because this word teaches you how to desire a lot. Yes.
学んでる。学んでる。学んでる。試してる。試してる。難しい、だってこの言葉が、たくさん欲望するやり方を教える。うん。
But don't teach you enough how to not desire.
でも欲望しないやり方は、十分には教えない。
I want to learn more how to desire less. And that's what you pray about amongst other things. I pray to I pray to different things depending on what uh what I'm I'm lacking and what I'm missing more.
欲望を減らすことをもっと学びたい。そしてそれが、他のことと一緒に、君が祈ってることなんだよね。足りないもの、もっと欠けてるものによって、違うものに祈る。
Um if I'm lacking peace, inner peace, then I will do one type of prayer.
うーん、平和が、内なる平和が足りないなら、一つのタイプの祈りをする。
But if I'm if I'm feeling in peace and I feel like there's so much that I have to celebrate, I then I pray and and give thank you.
でも平和を感じてて、祝うことがすごくたくさんあると感じるなら、それから祈って、ありがとうを言う。
I do more something that has to do with gratitude. in in the idea of of of um searching for balance from something greater than yourself and asking for that from somewhere.
感謝に関係することをもっとする。自分より大きな何かからバランスを探すアイデアの中で、どこかからそれをお願いする。
What what's at the top of your asking list?
お願いリストの一番上には何があるの？
I think that sometimes it's not about asking.
ときどき、お願いすることじゃないと思う。
It's about listening. It's about stopping maybe and listening. Is it maybe about projecting yourself towards something that is bigger than you and that reminds you that reminds you who you are.
聴くことなんだ。止まること、たぶん、そして聴くこと。自分より大きなものに向かって自分を投影することかもしれない、それが、自分が誰か思い出させる、思い出させる。
that reminds you your path. Um, so sometimes it's about asking for guidance when you don't see clear enough. Um, sometimes it's about asking for blessings for the people that you love.
自分の道を思い出させる。うーん、だからときどき、十分クリアに見えないとき、導きをお願いすること。うーん、ときどき、愛する人たちへの祝福をお願いすること。
Um, sometimes it's asking about uh peace, more inner peace maybe.
うーん、ときどき、平和についてお願いしてる、もっと内なる平和、たぶん。
So it each time it's different, but I find that I love this woman.
だから毎回違う、でもこの女性が好きなんだ。
and she's she's called Alana Portterero and she says that we should all pray even even if you don't believe even if you don't have faith she says that even if your prayer is
そして彼女はアラナ・ポルテレーロって呼ばれてて、信じてなくても、信仰がなくても、みんな祈るべきだって彼女は言う、たとえ祈りが
a is more like a pagan prayer she says that's still okay because you are projecting yourself toward towards what's beyond you and that there's um there's a way of like getting rid of
もっと異教の祈りみたいでも、それでもいいって言う、だって自分を超えたものに向かって自分を投影してるから、そして取り除くやり方がある、みたいな
Beneno of poison and I like that I think that we all do carry some sort of poison. We all have questions. We all carry questions. We all carry stain, you know.
ベネノの、毒の、そしてそれが好き、みんななんらかの毒を抱えてると思う。みんな質問を持ってる。みんな質問を抱えてる。みんな染みを抱えてる、わかる？
So I think that if you can in a way you can get closer to the source, you can get closer to what your center you can get closer to where you're supposed to be.
だから、ある意味できるなら、源に近づける、自分の中心に近づける、いるべきところに近づけると思う。
Who who are you supposed to be surrounded or what are you supposed to be around surrounded with?
誰に囲まれるべきなの、それとも何に囲まれてるべきなの？
Like if you understand that, I think you find more peace and you're happier and your life is just better, you know. Yes. Yes.
それがわかれば、もっと平和が見つかると思うし、もっと幸せで、人生がただ良くなる、わかる？ うん。うん。
I got to say something. I wish that I could play with you here to the game that they used to play, right?
言わせて。ここで君と、昔やってたゲームをプレイできたらいいのに。だよね？
because I feel like I'm enjoying this conversation so much and you're so good at two things could be right and two things can be very wrong I think okay I'm sure with it
だってこの会話をすごく楽しんでるし、君は二つのことが正しくもありえて、二つのことがすごく間違ってもありうるのが上手で、と思う、オッケー、それで確信がある
I want to play also I would love to play more ball uh games I don't know enough play tennis and play I squash you know played Did you ever play sports when you
あたしもプレイしたい、もっとボールの、うーんゲームがやりたい、十分知らない、テニスをして、スカッシュをして、わかる、やったことある？ 子供のときスポーツを
were a kid at all I used to dance okay that's that's athletic I used to dance and when I was Christina used to uh play soccer.
子供のころ、少しでも。昔ダンスしてた、オッケーそれはアスレチックだ、昔ダンスしてて、クリスティーナだったとき、サッカーをしてた。
Oh, you did? Did you like it, sister? Did she beat you?
おお、やったの？ 好きだった、姉さん？ 彼女は君に勝った？
She was she was amazing. She basically was a defenser. She was defense and I was constantly the one who scored the goal. How do you call it?
彼女はすごかった。基本的にディフェンサーだった。彼女はディフェンスで、ゴールを決めてたのはずっとあたし。なんて呼ぶ？
Mhm. Striker. Yep. I was striker. She was defense.
うん。ストライカー。うん。あたしがストライカー。彼女がディフェンス。
Which I think that is very much um it speaks to your relationship. Yeah.
それが、君たちの関係をすごく語ってると思う。うん。
No, no. She strikes a lot too. But I bet but but she defends me so much. Yeah, I think I have a lot. Yeah. Yeah. I mean, obviously that support that you have with with family is incredibly important.
いや、いや。彼女もたくさん打つ。でもきっと、でも彼女はあたしをすごく守ってくれる。うん、たくさんあると思う。うん。うん。つまり、明らかに、家族とのそのサポートは信じられないくらい大事。
I don't think you can make the decisions that you make, take the risks you take with the confidence that you obviously have without knowing that there are people who are going to keep
君がする決断、君が取るリスクを、君が明らかに持ってる自信で取れるとは思わない、いてくれる人たちが、保つ
it very honest with you and have your back.
それをすごく正直に、君に対して、そして君の背中を持ってる、って知らなきゃ。
Yeah, they got my back. My mother got my back. She always supported me so much. My dad also, like my sister, like I'm so lucky.
うん、背中を持ってくれてる。母が背中を持ってくれてる。いつもすごく支えてくれた。父も、姉みたいに、すごくラッキー。
Yeah. I have a really supportive family. You had a fun childhood. A good childhood.
うん。すごく支えてくれる家族がいる。楽しい子供時代だった。いい子供時代。
I think I know how to just uh get in my in my world like basically I would always be in my head and be having fun and just didn't care a lot and
自分の世界に入るやり方を知ってると思う、基本的にいつも頭の中にいて、楽しんでて、あんまり気にしてなくて
music played a huge role in you disappearing into that space.
その空間に消えていくのに、音楽がすごく大きな役割を果たしてた。
I think that in a way yes because I would I think I would dissociate a lot and I think I would be singing a lot in my head like I think there was
ある意味うんだと思う、だってすごく解離してたと思う、そして頭の中でたくさん歌ってたと思う、そこには
a lot of spoken melodies would get stuck and I would stay in like repetition with that and I wouldn't even listen what is happening or nothing I would just be here and yeah
たくさんの語られるメロディが引っかかって、それで反復の中にいただろう、何が起きてるかすら聴いてなくて、何も、ただここにいて、うん
I think that music music has been always there in a way yeah God is a stalker [laughter] No, but it's true. That's an impossible exercise. Okay.
音楽は、音楽はいつもそこにあったと思う、ある意味うん、神はストーカー。いや、でも本当だ。それは不可能なエクササイズ。オッケー。
Yeah. The the first person trying the first person of God in a song, it's an impossible. That's why it's already from a sense of humor point of view.
うん。神の一人称を試す最初の人、歌の中の神の一人称、それは不可能。だからすでにユーモアの感覚の点からなんだ。
But in title, what the title suggests isn't necessarily what the song says. It it it's not literal.
でもタイトルでは、タイトルが示唆するものは必ずしも曲が言うことじゃない。文字通りじゃない。
It's not like I I don't feel like, you know, you're doing a character assassination on on God's obsessive obsession with humanity or with yourself.
神の、人類への、あるいは君自身への、執着的な執着のキャラクター暗殺をしてる感じはしない、わかる？
It it feels far more like a like I'm not even sure who God is sometimes on this record. Sometimes I feel like it's in human form.
もっと、このレコードの上で神が誰か、ときどきわからない感じ。ときどき人間の形の中にいる感じがする。
It's in a relationship. Sometimes I think you're referring to yourself like I think it's an imperfect uh it's in a imperfect way because it's made from a human and humans.
関係の中にいる。ときどき君は自分自身を指してると思う、不完全な、不完全なやり方の中にある、だって人間から、そして人間たちから作られてるから。
So whatever it's made human made, it will be imperfect. just that it's and it's perfect. So yes, there will always be different ways of approaching it because I'm trying it's an exercise
だから人間が作ったものは何でも、不完全になる。ただそれ、そしてそれは完全なんだ。だからうん、近づき方はいつも違う、だって試してる、それはエクササイズ
an impossible exercise which is trying to put words and sounds into something that it's much beyond that.
不可能なエクササイズ、言葉と音を、それをずっと超えてるものに入れようとすること。
And you said in your post as well that you know like um I again to quote Lind Coleman, I hope I never find the one song that we all have in us, right?
そして投稿でも言ってたよね、わかる、うーん、またLeonard Cohenを引用すると、みんなの中にあるその一つの曲を、絶対に見つけないといい、だよね？
the idea to um have the space and the runway to create for as long as God will allow you to create.
神が作ることを許してくれる限り、作るためのスペースと滑走路を持つ、ってアイデア。
And yet when I listen to this album, it's almost like um it could be your life's work up to this point. It feels so powerful and impactful like almost a desperation to get it all out onto one record.
それでもこのアルバムを聴くと、ほとんど、この時点までのライフワークでありうる、みたいな。すごくパワフルで、インパクトがあって、全部を一枚のレコードに出し切りたい必死さみたいな。
Does that does that make sense? Go so much into it.
それは筋が通る？ そんなにその中へ行く。
That's interesting. I don't know what I felt though when I was doing it is that I don't know if something like this could be repeated, right?
それは面白い。やってるときに感じたのはわからないけど、こういうものが繰り返せるかわからない、だよね？
I really had the feeling that this just sometimes come maybe once. I don't know if something like this could at at this like level of intensity. I don't know if I could do it again.
これはときどき、たぶん一度だけ来る、って感覚が本当にあった。こういうものが、この強度のレベルで、またできるかわからない。
Were you emotional when you finished it or just relieved? I was about to have a mental breakdown.
終わったとき感情的だった？ それともただホッとした？ 精神的に崩壊しそうだった。
I really was about to because meeting the deadlines there was a point where it was like okay if you really don't turn it in for the vinyl right now uh this in next
本当にそうなりかけた、締め切りに会うことで、ある時点で、もし本当に今すぐヴァイナル用に出さないなら、うーんこれ、次の
the next week you have to uh release it next year and I was like something in me told me like I really cannot miss this window even if I it's so important the
次の週、来年にリリースしないといけない、って。そして、この窓は本当に逃せない、たとえ、すごく大事な、って中の何かが教えてた
the tempos creativos and I always respect them so I knew this album had to come out in this year.
テンポス・クレアティヴォスを、そしていつもそれを尊重してる、だからこのアルバムは今年出なきゃいけないってわかってた。
Mhm. I knew it was now. Something in me told me this you cannot uh extend forever like this has to come out a pushed myself so much and no say I I remember shaking all the time like because
うん。今だってわかってた。中の何かが、永遠に延ばせない、これは出なきゃ、って教えてた、すごく自分を押した、そしてノー・セイ、ずっと震えてたのを覚えてる、だって
that's how how much the level of stress was.
ストレスのレベルがどれだけだったか、そういう。
What were you What was the last song you were working on when you knew it was time to stop?
何を、やめる時だってわかったとき、最後に取り組んでた曲は何だったの？
M all of them at the same time.
うーん、全部同時に。
Oh wow. It's always all of it at the same time. It's always such a like um process of still simultane everything at the same time. Everything happening at the same time.
おお、すごい。いつも全部が同時。いつも、まだ全部を同時に、シミュルタネみたいなプロセス。全部が同時に起きてる。
And I'm trying to learn how to exist with the this uncertainty and all these things happening at the same time.
そしてこの不確実性と、同時に起きてるこれらの全部と一緒に存在するやり方を学ぼうとしてる。
And it felt like I had to abandon it and I had to like just send it to to be pressed in the vinyl.
そしてそれを捨てなきゃいけない感じがした、ヴァイナルにプレスされるために、ただ送らなきゃ、みたいに。
And then I changed more things [laughter] for the digital and some songs are a little bit different on the vinyl. Yeah, cuz it's been process. It's been a process through making this this project, different stages of it.
それからデジタルのためにもっと変えた、そして何曲かはヴァイナルと少し違う。うん、だってプロセスだったから。このプロジェクトを作るのを通したプロセス、その違う段階。
How long did you work with the London Symphony Orchestra for? Very little. Like maybe 3 days or something. 3 4 days. You did all of this in three or four days.
London Symphony Orchestraとは、どれくらい働いたの？ すごく少し。たぶん三日くらい。三、四日。これを全部、三、四日でやったの？
Everything was written. Everything was arranged. Everything was done. uh with so much like precision for us to go there, get there with the lasuras, with the scores and be like this is exactly what it needs to happen.
全部書かれてた。全部アレンジされてた。全部終わってた。うーん、すごく精度みたいなので、そこに行って、ラスーラスと、スコアを持って着いて、起きるべきことは正確にこれだ、って。
This is what we how we wanted it to be. We're just going to try a couple like in different intentions maybe, you know, more pianisimo or less or we're going to try this and that.
こうあってほしい、ってこと。たぶん違う意図で、いくつか試すだけ、わかる、もっとピアニシモか、少なくするか、これとあれを試す。
But we had to be very precise.
でもすごく正確じゃないといけなかった。
We had to be very much like okay no actually this should be um metallo no actually this should be just a timony doing this or that but it all was written like I
すごく、オッケー、いや実際これはメタルロであるべき、いや実際これはティモニーがこれかあれをやるだけであるべき、みたいにじゃないといけなかった、でも全部書かれてた、みたいに、あたしは
remember the hook of portalana it was inspired in a piano type of bass and but with a timony and you know we had that very much written and it was just getting to
Porcelanaのフックを覚えてる、ピアノタイプのベースにインスパイアされてて、でもティモニーで、わかる、それはすごく書かれてて、ただ着くことだった
the studio and being like this this is the line this is the melodic line we need boom we record it so super khiko There are songs on this record which um if you
スタジオに、そして、これがライン、これが必要なメロディライン、ドーン、録る、だからスーパー・キコ。このレコードには曲があって、うーん、もし君が
wanted to take them away and individualize them and present them before the album came out or do videos to that would go okay that that is a pure extension of the rose that
取り出して個別にして、アルバムが出る前に出したいか、あるいはビデオを、それでオッケーになる、あれは知ってるバラの純粋な延長だ、って
we know right um but you decided to introduce the album with Burkhine which is like yes yes which I love and and it's it's it's I mean it's so beautiful but so front
知ってるよね、うーん、でもアルバムをBerghainで紹介することにした、それは、うんうん、好きで、そして、つまりすごく美しい、でもすごく前
foot aggressive um it starts aggressive Eve Tuma ends it aggressive The statement is just so powerful. So, can you speak to the thinking process behind saying, "Hey, I'm back.
足で攻撃的、うーん、攻撃的に始まる、イヴ・トゥマが攻撃的に終わらせる。ステートメントがただすごくパワフル。だから、考えてたプロセスを話せる？ 「ねえ、戻った
Eat this." Why not though? Why not? I think that maybe it's a piece. It's represented representative of the the orchestral intention throughout the the album.
これを食え。」って言う背後の。でもなんでダメなの？ なんでダメ？ たぶん一つのピースだと思う。アルバムを通したオーケストラの意図を、代表して、代表してる。
And also, I think that uh I really love when an artist does that to me. I really like when an artist slaps me.
そしてまた、アーティストがそれをしてくれるのが本当に好き。アーティストにビンタされるのが本当に好き。
It's like it's doing something that I didn't uh maybe doesn't move musically that I didn't see coming.
音楽的に動かないかもしれない、来るのが見えなかった何かをしてる、みたいな。
Maybe just just provocation to some degree. A conscious provocation. Yeah. Just a little. Just a little. Not too much. But I feel like the album starts gentle.
たぶんただ、ある程度の挑発。意識的な挑発。うん。少しだけ。少しだけ。多すぎず。でもアルバムは優しく始まると思う。
I had the intention of starting in a soft way. So I think that when people experience the project and the album, they will have that the gentle feeling that I think it's so present throughout the album.
柔らかいやり方で始める意図があった。だからプロジェクトとアルバムを体験するとき、アルバムを通してすごく存在してると思う、その優しい感じを持つだろう。
But then a way of saying we are not going to do Moto Mommy again.
でもそれから、MOTOMAMIはもうやらない、って言い方。
That's releasing Bine, releasing Burgine first. It's releasing that and saying this is what we and also it's one of the most that are interven the orchestra.
それがBerghainを出すこと、最初にBerghainを出すこと。それを出して、これがぼくら、って言うこと、そしてオーケストラが介入する、いちばんのもののひとつでもある。
So I think that it's interesting that how how much the song is pushed in that one. The orchestra song is pushed in that one and it has all the elements.
だから、その曲で曲がどれだけ押されてるかが面白いと思う。その曲でオーケストラの曲が押されてて、全部の要素がある。
I feel like it has it all. It has the full orchestra. It has the full choir. It has it all. And I think maybe it's the way of saying mommy was minimalist few elements.
全部持ってる感じ。フルオーケストラがある。フルコーラスがある。全部ある。そしてたぶん、MOTOMAMIはミニマリスト、要素が少なかった、って言い方。
This is maximalism. Yes. like yes yes a lot uh you know big and so I think that bine shows that and there's all the elements in it named after the club in a way it's I think
これはマキシマリズムだ。うん。みたいな、うんうん、たくさん、うーん、わかる、大きくて、だからBerghainはそれを見せてると思う、そしてその中に全部の要素がある、ある意味クラブの名前で、ずっと
that I've always had a desire to go to that club but I never dare to say but it's always been there and then means ara de la means a group of uh trees
あのクラブに行きたい欲望はいつもあった、でも言う勇気はなかった、でもいつもそこにあった、そしてそれからアラ・デ・ラは、森の中の木の集まりを意味する
in the forest and I feel like we all kind of have these labyrinths in our heads, these forest of thoughts that you can get lost in, you know.
そしてみんな頭の中にこの迷路みたいなものを持ってる感じ、迷子になれる思考の森、わかる？
So, it's it's like Burkai cannot be that can be your mind. By it's your mind. It's everybody's mind.
だから、Berghainはそれでありえない、ありえる、君の心でありうる。バイ、それは君の心。みんなの心なんだ。
The meaning of the meaning of minds now that you've been able to establish with Bork. I feel like um you are a child of Bok in some respects.
意味の意味、心たちの、Berghainで確立できるようになった今。ある意味、君はBjörkの子供だ。
Mother mother for sure. So, now that you know you two have collaborated again and fell in this space to be able to work together again and figure it and and build on this um let's talk about
マザー、マザー、確実に。だから今、二人はまたコラボして、また一緒に働けるこの空間に落ちて、それを見つけて、これを築いて、うーん話そう
I love her. It's just the best. It's so inspiring. Most the most inspiring human maybe her is me. They're my two favorite my mothers and both are so free and I think both are so irreverent.
彼女が好き。ただ最高。すごくインスパイアされる。いちばん、いちばんインスパイアする人間、たぶん彼女があたし。二人は一番好き、あたしの母親たち、そして両方すごく自由で、両方すごく不遜だと思う。
both are so like I think it's it's what's most inspiring to me is how a woman can be a human being can be so so free and so amazing and so exciting and
両方すごく、女性が、人間が、こんなに、こんなに自由で、こんなに素晴らしくて、こんなに興奮させられて
so so many layers so contradictory is it's amazing the way they create the way they've been creating and they keep creating and they still have that passion and I saw Patty the other
こんなに、層がこんなにたくさん、こんなに矛盾してる、彼らが作るやり方はすごい、作り続けてきたやり方、作り続けてて、まだその情熱がある、そしてこの間Patti Smithを見た
day here in Madrid I saw her performing she was performing horsesh That was insane. That was that was a master class.
マドリードで、彼女が演奏してるのを見た、Horsesを演奏してた。あれは狂ってた。あれはマスタークラスだった。
Seeing her speed on stage with so much grace and so much like not giving a not giving a type of energy that I was like, wow. Yeah.
ステージで彼女のスピードを見る、こんなに優雅に、こんなに、気にしない、気にしないタイプのエネルギーで、あたしは、すごい、って。うん。
Wow. That's how we want to that's how we want to that's how it should always be. Just that you don't care. reminding yourself to not care. I think that's important.
すごい。そうでありたい、そうでありたい、いつもそうであるべき。ただ気にしない、ってこと。気にしないことを自分に思い出させる。それが大事だと思う。
I think there's a few mantras that I've had through this project. Not giving a It's obviously not import. But that's important. And then also I had this tea cup of tea.
このプロジェクトを通して持ってたマントラがいくつかあると思う。気にしない。明らかにインポートじゃない。でもそれが大事。そしてこのティーカップの紅茶があった。
Sorry. This m this Mac that I draw with my friend Alexa. And uh I wrote in it. It's like right, stretch the the bow and uh say the truth.
ごめん。この、友達のアレクサと描いたこのマック。そしてそこに書いた。みたいな、右、弓を伸ばして、そして真実を言え。
And that's what I all was all the time trying to do with this album.
そしてこのアルバムで、ずっとやろうとしてたのはそれ。
And I would wake up in the morning, do my tea in it, and I would always read it and I'll be like, okay, that's what we are aiming for today.
そして朝起きて、その中で紅茶を入れて、いつもそれを読んで、オッケー、今日の目指すところはそれだ、って。
If pressure makes diamonds, why aren't we all shiny? Yes, that is a very powerful statement. At least what I took from it, especially at the end of that.
圧力がダイヤを作るなら、なんでみんな輝いてないの？ うん、それはすごくパワフルなステートメントだ。少なくともそこから受け取ったもの、特にあれの終わりで。
Um, I haven't heard the song because I've only got the digital, but I read the lyrics. Yes. Yes. Yes. I'd love to know um what it means to you that statement.
うーん、その曲は聴いてない、デジタルしか持ってないから、でも歌詞は読んだ。うん。うん。うん。そのステートメントが君にとって何を意味するか、知りたい。
I feel like we are all we can all maybe relate in a way in in feeling some sort of pressure. At least that's or maybe maybe this that I'm saying it's wrong because maybe not everybody feels like this.
みんな、ある意味、なんらかの圧力を感じてることに関係できると思う。少なくともそれ、あるいは今言ってることが間違ってるかもしれない、だってみんなはこう感じないかもしれないから。
But a lot of people that I have around, I can tell that in a way we we carry some weight, right?
でも周りにいるたくさんの人、ある意味重さを抱えてるってわかる、だよね？
And um damn, how contradictory contradictorial it could be. You know that like that if pressure can make diamonds. Does this happen to us as humans?
そして、うーん、くそ、どれだけ矛盾しうるか、コントラディクトリアルに。わかる、圧力がダイヤを作れるなら、みたいな。それが人間のあたしたちに起こる？
Maybe it does. Maybe maybe there's some pressure applied from above that maybe brings the best of us out. Isn't that the story of this album of Lux to some degree?
たぶん起こる。たぶん、上からかかる圧力があって、たぶんいちばんいいものを引き出してくれる。ある程度、それはこのアルバム、LUXの物語じゃない？
You know, the pressure you felt at the end in order the deadlines missed. What you set out in front of you to try to achieve with this record, the expanse of it.
わかる、終わりに感じた圧力、締め切りを逃すために。このレコードで達成しようと自分の前に置いたもの、その広がり。
At least to me, I let pressure come to me as if I let that a hand can pressure me until the point where I allow pressure to happen in my life because I
少なくともあたしには、圧力が来るに任せる、手が圧力をかけてくるみたいに、人生の中で圧力が起こるのを許すところまで、だって
know that I'm in this mission of making music and I know that I wanted it. I know that this is not as soon as gradu I begged for it 10, 15 years ago.
音楽を作るこのミッションの中にいるって知ってるし、それを欲しかったって知ってる。これが、グラデュのすぐじゃないって知ってる、十年、十五年前に懇願した。
I begged for it. I I wanted it so bad.
懇願した。すごく欲しかった。
What did you want? I wanted this. I wanted to be able to be a musician and do it hopefully at the biggest scale possible and make the biggest uh uh projects and Thors, all of it.
何が欲しかったの？ これが欲しかった。ミュージシャンでいられて、願わくば可能ないちばん大きなスケールでやって、いちばん大きなプロジェクトとソーズ、全部を作りたかった。
I wanted it all. And I knew that maybe that would be being always in this kind of like Al the of breaking and and so that's where I I'm always I'm always in this [gasps] in this
全部欲しかった。そしてたぶんそれは、いつもこの、アルの、壊れる、みたいな中にいることだってわかってた、そしてだからそこ、いつも、いつもこの、この
about to break about to break uh and I I cannot complain. I can complain. That's not true. I can't complain.
壊れそう、壊れそう、うーん、そして文句は言えない。文句は言える。それは本当じゃない。文句は言えない。
I can't complain but but I can complain but I can but at the same time I I try to not complain too much because that was my desire.
文句は言えない、でも、でも文句は言える、でも、でも同時に、あんまり文句を言わないようにしてる、だってそれが欲望だったから。
I asked [snorts] God to push me and and so that's that's how I feel because that's always maybe brings the best.
神に押してって頼んだ、そしてだからそう感じてる、だってそれがいつも、たぶんいちばんいいものを連れてくるから。
How important was the arrival at the end of Mottom? Like it worked like I'm on the world stage. People are interested and excited by what I create.
MOTOMAMIの終わりに着くことは、どれくらい大事だった？ みたいに、うまくいった、世界のステージにいる。人は興味を持って、作るものに興奮してる。
They seem to like me as a person and who I am. How important was getting to that place for you to be able to make this record?
人として、誰であるかとして、好きみたいだ。このレコードを作れるために、あの場所に着くことは君にとってどれくらい大事だった？
M I guess what I'm asking is to your point you couldn't have done this two albums ago. I don't think so. No. And also I don't think that I could have sung how I'm singing in this album.
うーん、聞いてるのは、君のポイントに、二枚前のアルバムではこれはできなかっただろう、ってこと。そうは思わない。いや。そしてこのアルバムで歌ってるみたいに歌えたとも思わない。
What changed the way I'm writing for example it's allowing me to sing in another way also. You cannot rush things.
変わったのは、たとえば書いてるやり方が、別のやり方で歌うことも許してる。物事は急げない。
And in order for me I in Moto Mommy I remember I wanted already to be singing um pushing the boundaries of my voice how I did in this album but I I couldn't
そしてあたしにとっては、MOTOMAMIで、覚えてる、すでに歌いたかった、このアルバムでやったみたいに声の境界を押すことを、でもまだ
do that yet. Why? Because I because I've been thinking about it for these last years and I'm like why I couldn't?
それはまだできなかった。なんで？ だって、ここ数年それについて考えてて、なんでできなかったの、って。
And it's because the writing I wasn't able to write um in a way that I could allow myself to sing like this.
そして書くことが、こうやって歌うことを自分に許せるやり方で、書けてなかったから。
You need there has to be an openness and a surrender that just comes you know that just comes uh like this.
開かれてることと、明け渡すことが必要で、それはただ来る、わかる、ただこうやって来る。
If you are living like this, if you are allowing it to happen, if you are writing from this place, then you can sing from this place then you can explain things from this place cuz it's your truth.
こう生きてるなら、それが起こるのを許してるなら、この場所から書いてるなら、この場所から歌える、この場所から物事を説明できる、だってそれが真実だから。
Cuz it's your truth. And maybe my truth in that moment, even if I had the desire that my truth was another one and I was in another point of my life and I was going
だってそれが真実だから。そしてあの瞬間の真実は、たぶん、欲望はあっても真実は別のもので、人生の別の地点にいて、行ってた
it was another journey, another type of journey. And I I feel like spirituality has always been around for me in one way or another. It's always been around and my connection with God it's always been there.
別の旅、別の種類の旅だった。そしてスピリチュアリティは、ある形か別の形で、いつも周りにあった感じ。いつも周りにあった、神とのつながりはいつもそこにあった。
It feels like when that rash of speed of two three albums and mommy was so stylistic and more materialistic openly materialistic more more grounded less searching the verticality.
二、三枚のアルバムのスピードの発疹のとき、そしてMOTOMAMIはすごく様式的で、もっと唯物的で、オープンに唯物的で、もっと地に足がついて、垂直性を探すことが少なかった感じ。
It was more about oh the world is I'll take that. I'll take this. I'll take this. I'll take this.
もっと、ああ世界は、あれを取る。これを取る。これを取る。これを取る、ってことだった。
Yes. Like the world is my uh I like what Addison says. The world is my oyster.
うん。世界はあたしの、うーん、アディソンが言うのが好き。世界はあたしのオイスターだ。
[gasps] Yes. Like, let me let me just, you know, open this. Let me open this. Let me play with this. Let me make a jewelry out of this.
うん。みたいに、ただ、わかる、これを開けさせて。これを開けさせて。これで遊ばせて。これでジュエリーを作らせて。
Behind this door. And you'll give me this. I like this. This is Yes. Yes. Like kind of like this.
この扉の後ろ。そしてこれをくれる。これが好き。これは、うん。うん。みたいな、こんな感じ。
Kind of like I'm not going to try to talk too much about the contradictions that I might feel about being placed in this this I'm just going to have fun with it and
こんな感じ、この、この中に置かれてることについて感じるかもしれない矛盾について、あんまり話そうとしない、ただそれで楽しんで
explore it. But it is artificial. And I don't mean that as a criticism. There's a lot of artificiality that goes into this world.
探索する。でもそれは人工的だ。そして批判として言ってるわけじゃない。この世界に入る人工性はたくさんある。
Um, even the idea of going on stage and creating a connection for 2 hours is meaningful for those two hours, but it's the love is different. It's not like love.
うーん、ステージに上がって二時間つながりを作るってアイデアさえ、その二時間には意味がある、でも愛は違う。愛みたいじゃない。
It's like a different love. I get what you're saying, but also I think that anything that is extreme might be performative.
違う愛みたいだ。言ってることはわかる、でも極端なものは何でも、パフォーマティブかもしれないとも思う。
So being two hours exposed uh in a stage in front of a thousand people there there's an extreme in it, right?
だから二時間、ステージで、千人の前に晒される、その中に極端がある、だよね？
So yeah, I feel like I feel like anything these days I've been thinking about extreme femininity, it's performative as much as extreme masculinity.
だからうん、最近何でもについて考えてる感じ、極端な女性性、それは極端な男性性と同じくらいパフォーマティブだ。
And maybe it's just anything that it's pushed to the extreme will always have some sort of like performative. I think everything's performative, isn't it?
そしてたぶん、極端まで押されたものは何でも、いつもなんらかのパフォーマティブを持つ。全部パフォーマティブだと思う、だよね？
To some degree. I mean, you know, construction always in in what you how you present yourself to the world, in how you communicate to the others, there's always some sort of construction.
ある程度。つまり、わかる、構築はいつも、世界に自分をどう見せるかの中に、他者にどうコミュニケーションするかの中に、いつもなんらかの構築がある。
And maybe an artist does that maybe even to the more extreme, which is, you know, and then artists like David Bowie just accepted that.
そしてアーティストはそれをする、たぶんもっと極端にまで、わかる、そしてそれからDavid Bowieみたいなアーティストは、それをただ受け入れた。
They were just like 100% like I don't need to pretend that this is anything but shape shifting.
彼らはただ、百パーセント、これはシェイプシフト以外の何かかのように装う必要はない、みたいだった。
Yes. Or the same with uh Nick Cave which I've been obsessed during making this album.
うん。あるいはNick Caveも同じ、このアルバムを作ってる間執着してた。
I've been listening a lot and I I've been like listening a lot of back a lot of Mozer but also a lot of like u strokes Nick the Smiths but I really like
たくさん聴いてて、たくさん聴いてた、バックをたくさん、モーザーをたくさん、でもThe Strokesみたいなのもたくさん、Nick、スミス、でも本当に好きなのは
Nick Cave because of that acceptance of I can be something that I'm not all the time.
Nick Cave、その受け入れのせい、ずっとじゃない何かになれる。
I can sing a murder ballad right in front of you skull.
君の頭蓋骨の真ん前で、マーダー・バラッドを歌える。
I can tell the story in all of its layers. Yes, it's theatrical. There's so much theatrical and accepting that accepting that you are you're creating a fiction and I love I love that.
全部の層で物語を語れる。うん、演劇的だ。演劇的なものがすごくたくさん、そしてそれを受け入れる、フィクションを作ってるって受け入れる、そしてそれが好き、それが好き。
I heard you playing a bit of the strokes actually uh in your live stream.
ライブストリームで、実際The Strokesを少しプレイしてるのを聴いた。
And something about the way Julian sings and you can't quite make out what he's saying, so you have to leave it. I think he's so good. I I already told him I love his writing.
そしてJulianの歌い方の何か、何を言ってるか完全には聞き取れなくて、だから置いておかないといけない。彼はすごく上手だと思う。もう彼に言った、彼の書き方が好きって。
He thought that I was messing with him and I was not.
彼はからかわってると思った、でもそうじゃなかった。
And I meant it that I really like his writing and I I think he's so unique and I would love one day to write with him cuz I feel like you know when
そして本気だった、彼の書き方が本当に好きで、すごくユニークだと思う、いつか一緒に書きたい、だってわかる、他の人と書くとき
you write with other people they can push you to do things in in different ways and uh and to understand and understanding writing from another point of view and I I'm really interested
違うやり方で物事をやるように押してくれる、そして理解すること、別の視点から書くことを理解すること、そして本当に興味がある
in always learning. But that must be open to you now that you spent so much time writing just from your perspective.
いつも学ぶことに。でも今は開かれてるはず、自分の視点だけから書くことにこんなに時間を使ったんだから。
I mean this is this Lux has been an exercise in in pushing yourself as a writer to get to your 100%. Yes. And I didn't try to write 50 songs.
つまりこれは、このLUXは、書き手として自分を百パーセントまで押すエクササイズだった。うん。そして五十曲書こうとはしなかった。
No. You know that sometimes I've heard that people they I've never did this in an album of writing 60 songs, 50 songs and then you decide which ones you want to finish.
いや。わかる、ときどき人は、六十曲、五十曲書いてから、どれを終わらせたいか決める、ってアルバムで、これはやったことがないって聞いたことがある。
It's like that's not how I do. That's not what I did. I chose to do the pieces that I really wanted to do.
それは、やるやり方じゃない。やったことじゃない。本当にやりたかったピースをやることを選んだ。
like let's say an area and then um more a song more inspired in raya which is the sufi woman uh so with benerada in Islam which song is that um and there's [laughter]
たとえばaria、そしてそれから、もっと、ラヤにインスパイアされた曲、スーフィーの女性、うーん、だからイスラムのベネラダと、どの曲だっけ、うーん、そして
and there's Arabic in it. So, you know, like I was like, "Okay, I'm going to do a song like this and a song like this."
そしてその中にアラビア語がある。だから、わかる、「オッケー、こういう曲と、こういう曲をやる」って。
And I focus on this is the idea that I want to do and I execute it. And I don't try to make 50 songs. I try to do 18.
そしてこれに集中する、これがやりたいアイデアで、それを実行する。そして五十曲作ろうとしない。十八をやろうとする。
And you just finish them. Yeah. But you finish them. Yeah. And finish them.
そしてただ終わらせる。うん。でも終わらせる。うん。そして終わらせる。
You honor them. You don't sit down and go, "Okay, I'm uninspired by that." It's like, "No, I must push through and see this through."
それらを称える。座って「オッケー、あれにはインスパイアされてない」ってならない。「いや、押し通さないと、これを最後まで見ないと」って。
Yes. Yes. Exactly. Not opening a lot of paths. opening this as I was saying before and try to finish.
うん。うん。まさに。たくさんの道を開かない。前に言ってたみたいにこれを開いて、終わらせようとする。
Can you talk about the jugular for a second because that song is so powerful and so beautiful and the ending is just incredible and it sits so perfectly in the album sequence as
一秒、La Yugularについて話せる？ だってあの曲はすごくパワフルで、すごく美しくて、終わりがただ信じられなくて、アルバムの順番の中に完璧に座ってる
well. Can you tell us a little bit about the story behind that song?
も。あの曲の背後の物語を、少し話してくれる？
Yes. Um so this woman Ravia she used to say uh she used to speak and people would write what she was what she was saying and apparently she would talk a lot about the
うん。うーん、だからこの女性ラヴィア、彼女はよく言ってた、よく話して、人は彼女が言ってることを書いた、そしてどうやら神を愛することのアイデアについてたくさん話してた
idea of loving God not because trying to get a reward not because trying to do something out of fear.
報酬を得ようとするからじゃなくて、恐れから何かをしようとするからじゃなくて。
It should be just and there's also I think um something so beautiful when I've been reading more about Islam Islamica and it's so interesting how this conception of everything connected everything is connected
ただであるべきで、そしてまた、イスラム、イスラミカについてもっと読んでるとき、すごく美しい何かがあると思う、全部がつながってる、全部がつながってる、この考え方が
with everything right and I was trying to write uh and express that the best I could in the outro of it when I say grande right and then and then goes microact macro
全部と、だよね、そしてそれを書こうとしてた、できる限りいちばんよく表現しようと、そのアウトロで、グランデって言うとき、だよね、そしてそれからマイクロアクト、マクロに行く
and the joosition of it, right? And the stretch of it and uh that force that tension between both.
そしてそのジューシション、だよね？ そしてそのストレッチ、そして両方の間のその力、そのテンション。
It felt exciting to me how they between lines I could be pushing that stretching that and I think it might be maybe my favorite part.
ラインとラインの間で、それを押して、それを伸ばしてられるのが、興奮する感じがした、そしてたぶん一番好きな部分かもしれない。
Sometimes that feeling of the the grandeo I I list it's something I experienced and I wanted to put in a in a song. It's clear you have very high observation abilities.
ときどきそのグランデの感じ、リストする、経験したことで、曲の中に入れたかった。観察する能力がすごく高いのは明らか。
Um even just what you said about Los Angeles and how the trees grow against the pavement. I love that because it's so cool. It's like you think you won but you didn't.
うーん、ロサンゼルスについて言ったことだけでも、木が舗道に逆らって育つこと。それが好き、だってすごくかっこいい。勝ったと思うけど、勝ってない、みたいな。
We will win in the end. At the end we will win.
最後には勝つ。終わりには勝つ。
Yes. And all the the roots you call it all the roots.
うん。そして全部の、ルーツって呼ぶ、全部のルーツ。
Yeah. Yeah. It's a it's a very powerful lesson. It's such a simple thing. Most people step over them or walk their dogs over them. But it actually says everything you need to know which is we are temporary.
うん。うん。すごくパワフルなレッスンだ。すごくシンプルなこと。ほとんどの人はそれをまたぐか、犬をその上で歩かせる。でも実際、知る必要がある全部を言ってる、一時的だ、って。
Beautiful. Yes. And I like to not fight them.
きれい。うん。そしてそれらと戦わないのが好き。
when I walk in LA uh which I I would try to do here and there uh during the week just at least one hour I would just be like at night or in
LAを歩くとき、うーん、ここそこでやろうとしてた、週の間、少なくとも一時間、夜か
the morning just walking and listening to albums I would listen a lot of albums man the total I was trying to study classical music right so I would listen a lot of the
朝に、ただ歩いて、アルバムを聴いて、たくさんのアルバムを聴いたよ、トータル、クラシック音楽を勉強しようとしてた、だよね、だからたくさん聴いた
classics some chopen some bach some mal a lot of maler alenith granados fire lots of back a lot of um the sweets uh played by Paul Pocazal Pocazal really liked and so a
クラシックを、ショパンをいくらか、バッハをいくらか、マルをいくらか、マーラーをたくさん、アレニス、グラナドス、ファイア、バックをたくさん、うーんスイーツをたくさん、ポール・ポカザルが弾く、ポカザルが本当に好きで、だから
lot of cello a lot of strings lots of strings and a lot of mariaalas amazing a lot of mariaalas yeah which is my favorite of all time and so I would remember I
チェロをたくさん、弦をたくさん、弦をたくさん、そしてマリアーラスがすごくたくさん、すごい、マリアーラスをたくさん、うん、史上いちばん好き、だから覚えてる、あたしは
would just be walking in the in the street and maybe you could have a little bit of like the eye the roots no that like it's annoying but no later I would I
通りをただ歩いてただろう、そして少し、目、ルーツ、みたいなのがあるかもしれない、いや、それはうざい、みたいな、でもいや、あとで、あたしは
be friends with it of the fact that They make me go up and then they make me go down and and that I would see them and I would appreciate how strong they
その事実と友達になる、上に行かせて、それから下に行かせる、そしてそれらを見て、どれだけ強いか感謝するだろう
are big and and how amazing is that they just break the pimento. I really like when things break they break something that it's not supposed to be broken and that's what they do.
大きい、そしてピメントをただ壊すのがどれだけすごいか。物事が壊れるのが本当に好き、壊れるべきじゃないものを壊す、そしてそれが彼らのやること。
I want to talk to you about Memorialia.
Memóriaについて話したい。
Memorialia. Yes. Yes. Carmino wrote though that uh those lyrics.
Memória。うん。うん。でもカルミーノが書いた、あの歌詞を。
Carmen is a great writer and I love that she used this fo traditional and she shared it with me and she sent that and I was like wait this this is so crazy
カルメンはすごい書き手で、このフォ・トラディショナルを使ったのが好きで、それをシェアしてくれて、それを送って、待って、これはクレイジー、って
cuz this is so perfect this is the thing that I'm talking about in this album you know and how much you can forget who you were and and of who you are also
だってこれは完璧、このアルバムで話してること、これなんだ、わかる、自分が誰だったかをどれだけ忘れられるか、そして自分が誰であるかも
remember me in my imperfections how often people say when they're about to pass you know remember me fondly or think fondly of me, remember the good sides of me.
不完全さの中のあたしを覚えてて、人が逝きそうなとき、よく言うよね、好意的に覚えてて、好意的に思って、いい側を覚えてて、って。
It's like I just remember it all like and I like how you sing and there's a moment in that where your voice changes and it becomes a deeper resonant experience.
ただ全部覚えてて、みたいな、そして歌い方が好き、そこである瞬間、声が変わって、もっと深く響く体験になる。
Yeah, it's really like in that moment it's it's just a very powerful change in the way that you perform. What inspired you to do that?
うん、本当に、あの瞬間は、パフォーマンスの仕方のすごくパワフルな変化だ。それをやるのに何がインスパイアしたの？
These lyrics now after singing so with the chest so open and everything now there's a confessional moment.
これらの歌詞、胸をこんなに開いて、全部で歌ったあと、今、告白の瞬間がある。
A lot of times memories we there are memories that are real and there are others that are a little bit fabricated and there's a vulnerability in it.
たくさんのとき、記憶、本物の記憶もあれば、少し作られたものもあって、その中に脆さがある。
Yeah. I mean, right? Like there's both. And maybe I was just like, okay, this is kind of a confession to say that there might be memories of my life that I might be more true than others.
うん。つまり、だよね？ みたいな、両方ある。そしてたぶん、人生の記憶の中に、他より本当かもしれないものがある、って言う告白みたいな、って。
And maybe sometimes I explain it in a way and sometimes I explain it in another. But every time I explain it in that moment, if I'm explaining it, that's that's going to be my truth.
そしてたぶんときどきあるやり方で説明して、ときどき別のやり方で説明する。でもあの瞬間に説明するときはいつでも、説明してるなら、それが真実になる。
This is my truth and there's truth in it. And um I like how imperfect memory is.
これが真実で、その中に真実がある。そして記憶がどれだけ不完全かが好き。
And yeah, I think that it was just trying to have some dynamics in the scope where it would be a little bit more soft, lower.
そしてうん、スコープの中にダイナミクスを持とうとしてただけだと思う、もう少し柔らかく、低く。
I wanted to end with this with this list relic.
これで終わりたかった、このリスト、Reliquiaで。
Yeah. Yeah. True stories. Some some some Okay. A lot.
うん。うん。本当の話。いくつか、いくつか、いくつか、オッケー。たくさん。
Okay. Maybe a lot. Not. Who knows? You lost a lot of time in LA. Who knows? That's that's fact.
オッケー。たぶんたくさん。じゃない。誰が知る？ 君はLAで時間をたくさん失った。誰が知る？ それは事実だ。
Did you lose your heels in Milan? Um I think some I've missed because I I Yeah. I lose so many things every time I'm traveling in with suitcases.
ミラノでヒールを失った？ うーん、いくつか逃したと思う、だって、うん。スーツケースで旅行するたびに、すごくたくさんのものを失う。
I've learned how to travel with just one or two.
一つか二つだけで旅行するやり方を学んだ。
I'm trying to be better at it. Yeah. Keep it simple.
もっと上手くなろうとしてる。うん。シンプルに保って。
Keep it simple. Yeah. And then but then I'm if I lose the hill. Lost my smile in the UK.
シンプルに保って。うん。そしてそれから、でもそれから、ヒルを失ったら。UKで笑顔を失った。
[laughter] I've I've laughed a lot in UK also the way okay I did it's just that you know here and there it will be rainy and I lost my faith in DC yeah
イギリスでもたくさん笑った、やり方も、オッケーやった、ただわかる、ここそこに雨になる、そしてDCで信仰を失った、うん
the sky was born in Buenos Aries yes it's the most beautiful sky I've ever seen in my life the the sky is so close the sky is like you can reach it you
空はブエノス・アイレスで生まれた、うん、人生で見たいちばん美しい空、空がすごく近い、空は手が届くみたい、君は
could like almost like feelings like that you could eat it you could you could take the clouds and save it with you. You could, you know, like the sky is crazy there.
ほとんど、それを食べられるみたいな感じ、雲を取って、一緒に保存できる。できる、わかる、そこの空はクレイジー。
The colors and the the proximity. I cried in Japan. I love Japan.
色と、近さ。日本で泣いた。日本が好き。
Yeah. And Japan, Japan put me in my feelings.
うん。そして日本、日本は気持ちの中に入れてくれた。
Japan is like this justosition between playfulness and like wo park attraction like an amusement park. Uh w this that colors so much um stimulation. But I find it calming for my senses.
日本は、遊び心と、ウォー、公園のアトラクション、遊園地みたいなものの間の、このジュストシションみたい。うーん、これ、色がすごく、うーん刺激。でも感覚には落ち着きを感じる。
But also that coming also to a point where it's you're going to you're going to be in touch with that sadness that you didn't want to face or that whatever that nostalgia that
でもまた、それは、向き合いたくなかった悲しみに触れるところに来る、あるいはそのノスタルジア、その
whatever it's going to come out. You're not going to be able to fight it. That's how powerful Japan is.
何であれ、出てくる。それと戦えないだろう。日本はそれくらいパワフルなんだ。
We are finishing this conversation in Madrid. Yeah. There's a lousy love out there somewhere in Madrid. [laughter] me.
この会話をマドリードで終えてる。うん。どこかマドリードに、ろくでもない愛がある。あたし。
We're leaving it. I I had Yeah. I had a story. Mhm. A tough one. A tough tough love. Yeah.
それを残して去る。うん、あった。うん。話があった。うん。タフなやつ。タフでタフな愛。うん。
You are no saint, but I'm just I'm just a human. I'm just Rosalia.
君は聖人じゃない、でもただ、ただの人間なんだ。ただのロサリアなんだ。
But you're blessed. But I have so much blessings in my life that I that I always that I'm so grateful for. Yeah.
でも君は祝福されてる。でも人生に祝福がすごくたくさんあって、いつも、すごく感謝してる。うん。